<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glorious reward of faithful ministers declared and improved in a sermon upon the occasion of the funeral of that excellent minister of Jesus Christ Henry Newcome ... / by John Chorlton.</title>
            <author>Chorlton, John, 1666-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18271830</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18271830</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1629:113)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glorious reward of faithful ministers declared and improved in a sermon upon the occasion of the funeral of that excellent minister of Jesus Christ Henry Newcome ... / by John Chorlton.</title>
                  <author>Chorlton, John, 1666-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.P. and are to be sold by Zachary Whitworth bookseller in Manchester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within mourning borders.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Newcome, Henry, 1627-1695.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Glorious REWARD OF <hi>Faithful Miniſters</hi> Declared and Improved. IN A SERMON UPON The Occaſion of the Funeral of that Excellent Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt <hi>HENRY NEWCOME,</hi> A.M. Late Paſtor of a Congregation at <hi>Mancheſter</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN CHORLTON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>T. P.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Zachary Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107283:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107283:2"/>
            <head>To the Worthy and much Honoured Lady The Lady MERIEL MOSSLEY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R long and intimate Acquaintance with Reverend Mr. <hi>Newcome</hi> of Bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the Relation in which he ſtood to you, and the High Eſteem which he always found with you, together with your many Generous Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Kindneſs to his Perſon and Family, give you an undoubted Title to this Memorial of him. I am very ſenſible that what I have here done, or am able at any time to do, can neither be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his Name and Memory, nor merit your Ladiſhips Acceptance. But, your Candour, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, is equal to your Great Judgment; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I deſpair not of your Pardon where I am liable to Cenſure, nor can I doubt your Favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Reception and Patronage to what is any way capable of Approbation. I know your Prudence and Humility would diſpoſe you to an extream Reſentment, ſhould I dilate upon thoſe many Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Honourable Endowments, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:107283:3"/> you a moſt Conſpicuous Ornament of your Sex and Quality. Therefore, inſtead of diſplaying your Ladiſhips Exemplary Goodneſs, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally acknowledged, I ſhall pray that it may have a moſt diffuſive and powerful Influence upon others; may it convince them how vain the Attempt is of arriving at true Greatneſs, unleſs they firſt become truly Pious and Religious. And may it pleaſe the God of all Grace, to Sanctifie all his Diſpenſations to you, and to enrich you more and more with all Wiſdom, Grace and Felicity, that after a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Perſeverance in his Bleſſed Fear, you may be joyfully tranſlated to his Everlaſting Kingdom and Glory. <hi>So Prays</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips Moſt Obliged Humble Servant in the Goſpel <hi>John Chorlton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:107283:3"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, Eſpecially ſuch as lived under Excellent Mr. <hi>Newcome</hi>'s moſt Fruitful Miniſtry.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TWO things</hi> come under preſent Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. The <hi>following Diſcourſe,</hi> and the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of it. There is nothing to make the <hi>former</hi> unacceptable, but the <hi>latter.</hi> You have, here, a moſt Sublime Portion of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture very aptly explained, and uſefully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, ſo as to Miniſter Light, and Warmth, to them that read. <hi>That only</hi> in the whole, which is Grievous, is, That we are told Worthy Mr. <hi>Newcome</hi> is Dead! <hi>This</hi> is a gloomy <hi>Theme!</hi> and is only capable of a more Lightſome, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Aſpect from the Brightneſs of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Luſtre of the Stars, into which ſo Wiſe and Powerful Preachers of the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel are at length transformed, as this Diſcourſe excellently ſhews. In the mean time, this is a Loſs which few can eſtimate, though they that ſuffer it are very many. It may be truly
<pb facs="tcp:107283:4"/> ſaid of <hi>ſuch a Man,</hi> as <hi>unknown and yet well known.</hi> They that knew him beſt, could know but a ſmall part of his true and great Worth, and might always apprehend when they knew moſt of him, there was ſtill much more that they knew not. His moſt <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>inartificial Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> ſtill drawing a Vail over his other Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; Which it <hi>hid,</hi> and <hi>adorned,</hi> at once. So as the Appetite of knowing more, muſt always meet with a <hi>Check</hi> and an <hi>Incitation</hi> at the ſame time. There was in him a large Stock of <hi>Solid Learning and Knowledge, always</hi> ready for uſe; for <hi>Oſtentation, never. Conſcience</hi> the moſt ſtrict, and ſteady to it ſelf, and the remoteſt from Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoriouſneſs of other Men. <hi>Eloquence</hi> without <hi>any Labour of his own,</hi> not imitable by the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Labour of another.</hi> O the ſtrange way he had of Inſinuating and Winding himſelf into his Hearers Boſoms! I have ſometimes heard him, when the only thing to be regretted was, that the Sermon muſt ſo ſoon be at an end. <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> ſo Facetious and Inſtructive together, that they who enjoy'd it, if they were capable of improving it, could ſcarce tell whether they went away from him more <hi>edified,</hi> or <hi>delighted. He was a burning and a ſhining Light.</hi> O <hi>Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter!
<pb facs="tcp:107283:4"/> Mancheſter!</hi> that ancient, famed, Seat of Religion and Profeſſion, May <hi>Capernaum</hi>'s <hi>Doom</hi> never be thine! May thy <hi>Heyrick, Hollingworth, Newcome,</hi> and thy Neighbours <hi>Angier, Harriſon,</hi> and divers more, never be Witneſſes againſt thee! They are Dead! <hi>And all Fleſh is Graſs, but the Word of the Lord endureth for ever, Even that Word of the Goſpel which hath by</hi> them <hi>been preached to you.</hi> It never dies. And may it ſtill abide with you, and in you. O labour to <hi>hold forth the Word of Life,</hi> that ſuch as have labour'd among you, may <hi>rejoyce in the day of Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>they have not run in vain, nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd in vain.</hi> Let it appear you are the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſt, miniſtred by them, to be known and read of all Men;</hi> So what there appear'd of Chriſt in them, will, as in another Edition, be ſeen in you. And thus will the Memory of <hi>this your Laſt deceaſed Paſtor,</hi> be beſt preſerved among you, when you ſhall every one diſcern Mr. <hi>Newcome</hi> ſtill, in each others <hi>Savoury Speech, pleaſant and compoſed Looks, becoming Behaviour, and regular well-ordered Converſation. This</hi> will make the Love of him live ſtill in your Hearts, which will no doubt appear and be exerciſed towards any of his, you have yet ſurviving
<pb facs="tcp:107283:5"/> among you, <hi>to whom you may ſhew kindneſs for his ſake.</hi> Thus you may let the World know your Love to him did not die with him, nor was buried in his Grave. You will by <hi>real Proofs</hi> teſtifie your value of him, whoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, at laſt, gave <hi>real Proof,</hi> that <hi>he ſought not yours, but you.</hi> I pray God a double Portion of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Spirit may reſt upon your <hi>remaining Eliſha.</hi> And am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in our Common Lord <hi>J. HOWE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107283:5"/>
            <head>The Glorious Reward of Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters declared and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. In a Sermon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Daniel 12.3.</bibl>
                  <p>And they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS is a Conſolatory Paſſage annexed to a Diſmal Propheſie, wherein the Divine Meſſenger relates under ſeveral Myſterious Figures, the many Strange and Various Revolutions that ſhould Influence the Affairs of the Church in future Ages. After which he proceeds to diſcloſe the final Reſult of all thoſe mighty Changes; And thereby to obviate the Diſcouragements which would ariſe from the Foreknowledge of them. And firſt there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation propounded generally to all that are Holy and Good. Such ſhall <hi>awake</hi> at the Reſurrection <hi>to everlaſting Life,</hi> when all Ungodly Men (but more eſpecially all Perſecutors, and thoſe who through their Brutal Violence, or baſe Flatteries, became Apoſtates from the true Religion) ſhall be covered with <hi>Shame and everlaſting Contempt.</hi> But as Miniſters have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107283:6"/> commonly the largeſt Share in the Calamities which befall the Church; ſo they have for their better Support and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, an Eminency and Preference aſſigned them in that Glory, the very leaſt and loweſt Degree of which, far tranſcends the Value of all their Labours and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
            <p>There are different Degrees of Glory to be conferred upon Perſons in the other World, in a juſt Proportion to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Meaſures of Perſonal Holineſs and Publick Uſefulneſs, whereby they have ſignalized and diſtinguiſhed themſelves in this.</p>
            <p>By <hi>thoſe that are Wiſe,</hi> ſome underſtand Religious Perſons, who are ſubject to the Inſtruction and Conduct of their Teachers. But I ſhall wave this Senſe, and conſider <hi>the Wiſe</hi> in the former Clauſe, as importing the ſame with <hi>thoſe that turn many to Righteouſneſs</hi> in the latter.</p>
            <p>The word here tranſlated <hi>Wiſe,</hi> is alſo rendred Teachers, and Chap. 11. v. 33. both Phraſes are put together as Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valents, or at leaſt filling up the ſame Character; <hi>They that underſtand among the People ſhall inſtruct many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that make a difference between <hi>the Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>they that turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> are likewiſe obliged to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between the Brightneſs of the Firmament, and that of the Stars; whereas it is (more probably) one and the ſame Metaphorical Reſemblance under a grateful Variety of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. So that the Phraſe appears to be doubled, that it might be more Emphatical, and the better amplifie and ſet forth the matter intended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Wiſe,</hi> then, are the Miniſters of the Church, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as the prime Veſſels in which (under the Mediator) the Treaſures of Divine Wiſdom are repoſited; that by them a Supply thereof may be regularly and ſtatedly conveyed to the ſeveral parts of God's Holy Church. <hi>Thoſe that turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> are ſtill the ſame Perſons conſidered as Faithfully and Succeſsfully employing the Gifts and Graces they have received, <hi>To turn the Diſobedient to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Juſt.</hi> 'Tis not Mens being qualified with Gifts, nor their being obliged by their Office and Profeſſion, <hi>to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107283:6"/> turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> that will entitle them to any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at all, much leſs to one that is ſo Superlatively Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent. There muſt be, at leaſt, when thoſe are ſuppoſed, a Sincere Deſire, manifeſting it ſelf in fervent and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Endeavours, to <hi>open the Eyes of Sinners, and to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God.</hi> For, ſhould we ſuppoſe a Perſon devoted to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Office, not only to pretend to it, but to be really, under God, the Inſtrument that effects this great Work of Converſion, it would avail him nothing, if at laſt it appears that this Change was never wrought upon himſelf. Where the Succeſs is owing only to a Form and Appearance of Sanctity, which the Miniſter aſſumed and managed with much Artifice; the very Perſons that ſuch an Hypocrite hath turned to Righteouſneſs, will bear a Subſtantial and Irrefragable Teſtimony againſt him. And on the other hand, He that ſincerely performs his part, ſhall not loſe his Reward, whatever the Succeſs be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though</hi> Iſrael <hi>be not gathered, yet ſhall he be glorious in the Eyes of the Lord, and his God ſhall be his ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 49.5. The Promiſe in the Text, in the letter of it, doth moſt expreſly belong to thoſe whoſe Labours are ſucceeded with anſwerable Fruit; but the Intent of it undoubtedly extends to all Faithful Miniſters. The Matter is thus ordered, that we may have a more natural and ardent Breathing towards the Succeſs of our Labours, and that our Purſuits after this great End may be more Vigorous. If we underſtand by <hi>The Wiſe</hi> Holy Faithful Teachers in general, and by <hi>thoſe that turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> the moſt eminently Laborious and Succeſsful among them; all that are <hi>qualified</hi> for this Reward, will be included in the Letter of the Promiſe, and this ſhadow of an Objection clean removed. Their <hi>Shining as the Brightneſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars,</hi> &amp;c. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, That as the Luminaries in the Firmament are the greateſt Ornament in the viſible Heavens, ſo are Faithful Miniſters of the Intellectual World; where they ſhall ſhine with incomparable Brightneſs in the Manſions of Glory, amongſt the Societies of Glorified Saints. The Celeſtial
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107283:7"/> Splendour to which they ſhall be advanced, will exceed all earthly Glory, as much as the pure Azure Sky doth this dull and dirty Clod of Earth. The Glory of the Stars may be alluded unto in this place rather than that of the Sun (to which this Reward is elſewhere compared) upon ſeveral Accounts. <hi>Christ Jeſus, the Son of Righteouſneſs, will ever be the chiefeſt Glory of the Church,</hi> both whilſt Militant and when Triumphant. The brighteſt Conſtellation of Miniſters ſhines but with a diminutive as well as derived Luſtre in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of him. Beſides which, it more aptly refers us to Multitudes of theſe Holy Inſtructors; and may intimate to us, that even amongſt theſe, <hi>One Star differeth from another Star in Glory.</hi> This ſhining is ſaid to be <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> They ſhall not only ſhine in Fame and Renown through a long courſe of time upon Earth, but in the Perfection of Light and Glory in the Heaven of Heavens for ever more.</p>
            <p>The words are an entire Propoſition of themſelves, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting thus much, <hi>That all Wiſe and Faithful Miniſters, that turn many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall poſſeſs an eminent degree of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Glory for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Proſecution of which, I ſhall do theſe three things:
<list>
                  <item>1. Deſcribe the Subjects to whom theſe high degrees of Glory are promiſed.</item>
                  <item>2. Demonſtrate the Certainty of this Truth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold the Reaſons why Miniſters ſhall be ſo plenteouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</item>
                  <item>3. I ſhall attempt a Manifeſtation of that excellent Glory, in part, and ſo far as will ſuit with our preſent Deſign; and then apply the whole.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subjects to whom theſe high Degrees of Glory are promiſed, are Wiſe and Faithful Miniſters, that approve themſelves to be ſuch, by turning many to Righteouſneſs. They themſelves firſt turn to Righteouſneſs, and are thereby prepared and diſpoſed to employ all their Abilities and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to convert others. Such are not ſatisfied with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107283:7"/> Upbraiding and Daunting wicked Men, or Shaming and Reſtraining them from their manifeſt Impieties. It does not ſuffice them to reclaim Notorious Offenders, only ſo far as to reduce them to a more Moral and Decent Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. It is natural to Faithful Miniſters to endeavour the Propagation of the ſame Vital Principle of Holy Living, and <hi>the ſame Union with the Lord Jeſus, the Head and Fountain of it,</hi> which themſelves believe and Experience. Faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>covet</hi> moſt earneſtly <hi>to change</hi> the very Tempers and Diſpoſitions of Men, from their natural Probity, to an Holy Aptitude and Sufficiency for Gracious and Heavenly Operations. They rejoyce in every Advance that is made towards the Divine Life; but that Divine Life it ſelf (in Sincerity at firſt, and afterwards in the Progreſs and final Conſummation of it) is what they preſs after themſelves, and above all things, with the moſt aſſiduous Application, endeavour to promote in their Hearers and People.</p>
            <p>Their buſineſs is to illuminate the Minds of Men, to convince their Conſciences, to rectifie their Judgments, and perſwade their Wills, to a ſound and deep Repentance for their paſt Miſcarriages, to a preſent Reformation of what is amiſs in their Hearts and Lives, and to a fixed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of walking with God and their Fellow-Creatures (eſpecially thoſe of the ſame Holy Chriſtian Profeſſion) in all Purity. 'Tis to make Men impartially and univerſally Good: Pious towards God, Juſt and Charitable towards their Neighbours, Sober, Chaſt and Humble in their whole Deportment. 'Tis to render them Uſeful and Exemplary in their particular Stations; and by all this to make Men Bleſſings to themſelves, the Church, and the World; that having Served and Honoured the God that made and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them, in this their Pilgrimage, they may arrive in his due time at <hi>the fullneſs of Joy, which is in the Preſence of God, and the Pleaſures for evermore which are at his right hand.</hi> Nor is it their Buſineſs, only to inform Perſons of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Perſonal Inherent Righteouſneſs, but alſo to <hi>acquaint them with the Perſon, the Offices and Righteouſneſs of the Mediater, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, God bleſſed for ever:</hi> On
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107283:8"/> the account whereof, and for whoſe ſake all their Sins are pardoned, and their Sincere, though Imperfect Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances ſhall be accepted, their Perſons juſtified, and their Souls and Bodies eternally Saved. The means whereby they carry on this great Work, are principally Holy and Powerful Preaching of God's Bleſſed Word, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Innocency and Purity of their Lives, together with their Patient and Conſtant Suffering of Reproach and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecution, when called to it, for the Vindication of thoſe Truths which they preach, profeſs and practiſe. If by theſe and all other inſtituted means, they prove inſtrumental (through the Co-operation, and principal Efficiency of the Holy Ghoſt) to turn one Soul to Righteouſneſs, it is matter of greater Joy to them, than all other Acqueſts could be. But there is not a Faithful Miniſter in the Church of God, that deſires not, above all things, to gain many and many Souls to Chriſt, whatever the Fooliſh World think of it, or may make it coſt them for ſo doing. Every ſuch Miniſter would be glad to have that fulfilled in himſelf, which is propheſied of <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.16. <hi>And many of the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall he turn to the Lord their God.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Sinners being the firſt and great Work of a Miniſter, is here put for all that is ſubſequent upon it. <hi>They</hi> are alſo careful to preſerve and <hi>perfect</hi> the Work of Grace in the Souls that <hi>are turned</hi> to Righteouſneſs <hi>by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The next Particular I am to account for, is to clear the <hi>Certainty</hi> of this Truth, and to unfold the Reaſons of God's proceeding in this manner with his Faithful Miniſters. The Certainty of it is evident both from this and other places of Scripture: <hi>They ſhall ſhine,</hi> &amp;c. They are qualified for, and <hi>have a Right</hi> to an Extraordinary Reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a more bright and maſſy Crown of Glory than others muſt expect. This is and ever hath been the Priviledge of Miniſters, under all God's Diſpenſations to the Church, by vertue of the Conſtitution of the Kingdom of Grace. And as all ſuch Rights are now already ratified above, ſo by the Conſtitution of that glorious Kingdom, all that die poſſeſt of them, ſhall be ſolemnly inveſted with, and admitted to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107283:8"/> their proper and peculiar Rewards immediately upon their Diſſolution. The Holy Angels themſelves will aſſiſt at their Inthronization, and the whole Heavenly Hoſt will chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully joyn their Applauſes to it. To this Conſideration we may in part aſcribe it, that Heaven it ſelf is ſtiled <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Boſom,</hi> Luke 16.22. And that the ſitting <hi>down with Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matt. 8.11. is an Expreſſion ſetting forth the Felicity of that State; as if it were the preſence of ſuch prime Miniſters that made, and muſt therefore denominate and deſcribe the Glory of it. Hence it is that <hi>Twelve Thrones</hi> are promiſed to the Twelve Apoſtles, Matt. 19.28. and their names inſcribed on the <hi>Twelve Foundations</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> Rev. 21.14. And as this proves the Apoſtles dignified above others, not only Chriſtians but Miniſters, ſo it genuinely infers, that thoſe who ſucceed them in the Office of the Goſpel-Miniſtry, and in the Fidelity and Diligence wherewith they diſcharged that Holy Function, ſhall be joyned with them in the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of an extraordinary Bliſs. But moſt clearly is this diſtinction laid down in that Promiſe of our Saviour, <hi>He that receiveth a Prophet,</hi> &amp;c. Matt. 10.41. where the Rewards of a Prophet, and of a Righteous Man, are as clearly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed as their Perſons and Stations. And as it would be too bold a Reſtriction to confine either of them to this mortal State, ſo there can be no doubt but the difference lies in the Excellency of that which is firſt mentioned above the other.</p>
            <p>Thus it appears that Faithful Miniſters ſhall enjoy an <hi>eminent Reward</hi> in Glory from the Tenour of Holy Writ. But becauſe all the Works of God carry the Signatures and Impreſſions of his infinite Rectitude upon them, and are Harmonious, and conform both to <hi>his</hi> Perfections and to each other: I ſhall further endeavour to ſhew the Wiſdom and Juſtice of the Divine Proceedings in this caſe. And firſt we may note in the general, that nothing is more becoming the Wiſdom and Juſtice of Almighty God, than to diſpenſe Rewards agreeably to the Meetneſs and Capacity of the Receivers. Now the turning of many to Righteouſneſs, is a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107283:9"/> Work of ſuch <hi>Heroical Virtue,</hi> that it is highly rewardable in it ſelf, and more pleaſing to him to whom the Diſpenſation of the future Glory belongs, than any other Service what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Therefore though there be no Merit of Equivalence in the Work, that might claim a Reward in the way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative Juſtice, yet it is greatly expedient to the Ends of Divine Government, that ſuch a Reward ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and promiſed to, and expected by Faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and if ſo, it muſt certainly be juſt that it ſhould be conferred on them. That the Service we are ſpeaking of, is ſo highly rewardable, will appear from this Conſideration. Beſides its being an Act of Obedience to God, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator (which it partakes in common with all other Acts of <hi>Evangelical obedience</hi> and Duty, to make it <hi>rewardable</hi>) it obtains a vaſt Preheminence of all others, in regard of its Intrinſick Excellency, its grand and univerſal Importance, and the amazing and almoſt inſuperable Difficulties that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it; than which, there can ſcarce be more proper Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities thought of, to recommend any Service, or to render a Perſon the meeteſt and moſt capable Subject of a <hi>Glorious Retribution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. That this is a Work of great Excellency and Worth in it ſelf, appears from many Conſiderations. Firſt, The Endowments and Qualifications which it ſuppoſes and requires. What Knowledge of the Myſteries of Religion, what Acquaintance with the Deceits of Mens Hearts, and the Wiles of the Devil, what a firm Belief of Divine Revelation are indiſpenſably required, to conſtitute a full Capacity for the Work and Office of a Goſpel-Miniſter?</p>
            <p>What Love to God, and ſeeking of his Glory, what a Thirſting after the Salvation of Mens Souls, what Faith in God, and the Promiſes for Aſſiſtance and Protection are neceſſary to a ſerious and deliberate Undertaking of this great Work?</p>
            <p>What Zeal and Courage to ſurmount all Oppoſition; what Prudence to manage abſtruſe and difficult Caſes; what Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Meekneſs to bear with Affronts, Calumnies and open Injuries from Adverſaries; what Candour to decline
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107283:9"/> Miſtakes, and prevent Miſunderſtandings, and a great many little Surmiſes and Jealouſies amongſt their Friends and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers; what Vigilancy to nip Miſchief in the Bud; what Moderation and Self-denial in beating with the Infirmities of the Beſt; what Tenderneſs and Fidelity to treat thoſe that offend, ſo as to recover them to Repentance; are viſibly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to carry on the Miniſtry?</p>
            <p>What unwearied Diligence and Conſtancy in publick and private Exerciſes, Preaching, Praying, viſiting the Sick, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving Offenders, reſolving Doubts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt he exerciſe, that would be a Miniſter to purpoſe? and what reſolute Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World, and all that ſavours of it, muſt he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that would turn many to Righteouſneſs?</p>
            <p>Beſides all that exemplary Holineſs which is neceſſary for all Chriſtians, and will be moſt carefully attended to, and ſtrictly exacted from thoſe that pretend to this great Office. Secondly,</p>
            <p>The Excellency of the <hi>Work</hi> is manifeſt from the ſubject matter about which it is converſant: The precious immortal Souls of Men; their Underſtandings, their Hearts, their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, their Lives, are under its Inſpection and Government.</p>
            <p>To Miniſters it belongs to proclaim the glad Tidings of the Goſpel; to expound the Oracles of God; to ſpeak to Men in the Name of the Lord by Authority received from him, about matters of everlaſting Concernment; to preſent the Confeſſions, Supplications and Thankſgivings of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto God; to apply the Seals of the New Covenant, to admit Perſons into the Communion of the Church, and upon juſt occaſion to exclude them from it by righteous Cenſures, and again to abſolve them and receive them to Favour upon their Repentance. Thirdly,</p>
            <p>The Excellency of the Miniſterial Work will be further illuſtrated and evinced from the relation they ſtand in to God, as the principal Agent that employs and gives them Succeſs; under him they Miniſter for the Demonſtration of his glorious Power and tremendous Juſtice, the Diſplays of his unſearchable Wiſdom and inviolable Truth, the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his ineffable Goodneſs and Love to moſt Unworthy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107283:10"/> Sinners, and for the Impreſſions of his Divine Purity. Thus Miniſters are <hi>Workers together with God,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.1.</p>
            <p>They officiate in that grand Deſign of Saving Elect Souls, which God from all Eternity framed, and will accompliſh through all the Periods of time. In Subordination to God as Creator, they endeavour to bring Souls back from their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Apoſtaſie, to the Fountain of their Beings, and of all Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. In Subordination to God as Redeemer, they publiſh the Heavenly Miſſion and Doctrine of the Lord Jeſus, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Evidences that confirm both; they promulgate his Laws, and declare the Terms of Salvation unto Men, and ſo help to apply his Sufferings, together with all the Vertues of his glorious Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Interceſſion and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion at God's right Hand. Whilſt they addreſs the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Mens Souls by outward Miniſtrations, the Holy Spirit inwardly and more immediately and effectually touches and moves them with a ſecret vital Energy, impregnates them with Godlike Diſpoſitions, and repleniſhes them with a victorious Strength and Activity for God and Glory.</p>
            <p>Which infers <hi>a fourth Conſideration</hi> enhanſing the value of the Miniſtry; The Conſideration (I mean) of the Sublime Excellency of the Work which their Endeavours tend to, and terminatein. And what is that? But the Pardon of Mens Sins, and a mutual Reconciliation between God and Sinners, together with the reſtoring of God's Image upon Man, and the Glory of Man's Allegiance unto God. Than which no Succeſs can be more Bleſſed, no Service more Rewardable. Which leads us to the ſecond General Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Turning Souls to Righteouſneſs is therefore highly Rewardable, becauſe it is a Work of grand Importance, and of univerſal Conſequence. So St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of it, Chap. 5. 19, 20. <hi>Brethren, if any of you do err from the Truth, and one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, Let him know that he which converteth the Sinner from the Error of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of Sins.</hi> How nearly is the Glory of God intereſſed in the Succeſs of the Miniſtry, and how much doth the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happineſs or Miſery of Immortal Souls depend upon it? 'Tis this whereby God ordinarily enlarges his Son's Kingdom,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107283:10"/> and drives Satan out of his Uſurp'd Dominions. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Church, either as Militant on Earth, or Triumphant in Glory, we ſhall find that 'tis the Succeſs of the Miniſtry in turning Souls to Righteouſneſs, that daily adds new Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to both theſe Illuſtrious Societies. Whether we only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the Family, or particular place and Vicinity whereto we belong; or the Congregation of profeſſed Chriſtians into which we are incorporated; or whether we enlarge our Thoughts to the State of the Nation or Kingdom where God hath caſt our Lot; or even to that of the World and of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general; it will ſoon appear how neceſſary and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant the Work is, on which all theſe ſo far depend, as to become every day liker to Heaven or Hell, as it either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails and proſpers, or is obſtructed and fruſtrated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3. As it is a Work of great Excellency and Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo it is extreamly difficult. How hard is it to perſwade Men to change their Judgments, Affections, Reſolutions, or Practiſe in any matter whatſoever, about which they have been long fixed and determined? But to turn Men from one State, Temper, and Carriage, to another directly contrary, and that not in one inſtance or two, but in the main bent of their Souls, and the Tenour of their Lives, <hi>muſt certainly be one of the hardeſt Tasks in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that turns many to Righteouſneſs, muſt perſwade them to deſpiſe, abhor and reject thoſe ſinful Vanities and Pleaſures which heretofore they eſteemed, loved, purſued, embraced and even adored above all things; ſo difficult this Work is. And yet it muſt be accompliſhed principally by the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Spiritual and Inviſible Objects; by propoſing diſtant and furture Rewards; inſtead of preſent palpable Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which have already made very violent and prevailing Impreſſions upon the Mind, and ſtrangely corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved the Imagination, Senſes, Appetites and Paſſions that have been all along careſſed by them.</p>
            <p>This leads us to conſider the manifold Oppoſition that is conſtantly made to this great Work; every part of which is ſufficiently formidable, but the Combination of all Adverſaries together is moſt wonderful and terrible. There is not a Sinner
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107283:11"/> converted, but Satan, the World and the Fleſh, are conquered and baffled in their moſt furious Efforts; and all their Politick Machinations defeated. How many Deviliſh Suggeſtions muſt be rejected? How many Solicitations from wicked Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions repulſed? How many evil Habits, that are founded in the very Conſtitutions of Perſons, muſt be extirpated? How many plauſible Temptations, that are interwoven with Mens Callings and Civil Circumſtances in the World, muſt be vanquiſhed and trampled under foot? Every Soul that is converted is like a Brand pluckt out of the Fire. But if we conſider the Imbecility of the beſt and ableſt Inſtruments, the Difficulty is yet greater.</p>
            <p>We have this Treaſure in earthen Veſſels; and that ever ſo frail a Compoſition ſhould daſh in pieces the Strong-holds of Satan, doth greatly increaſe the Wonder. Both the Gifts and Graces of the moſt eminent Miniſters are far from being pefect; their bodily Strength is limited within narrow bounds, and they often meet with Diſtractions and Avocations which unavoidably interrupt their greateſt Aſſiduity. Nay, ſo obſtinate is the Difficutly of turning one ſingle Soul to Righteouſneſs, that upon a juſt Computation it will be found vaſtly to exceed all Humane Power; ſo that the Attempt were vain and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and fit only to be buried in deſpairing Thoughts, were it not for the promiſed Concurrences of a Divine Power, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely ſuperiour to all Difficulties whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But as this Divine Power is not leſs to be magnified, becauſe it attains its end by the Miniſtry, ſo the Difficulties which Miniſters conflict with, are not therefore to be made light of, becauſe this Divine Power interpoſeth it ſelf. Since he that worketh by the Miniſtry as his Ordinance, works by the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Induſtry of Miniſters, as that Creature-agency, by means whereof he will make the Ordinance effectual.</p>
            <p>Thus it appears, that turning Souls to Righteouſneſs, is a Work highly rewardable, through the alone Merit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Paul</hi> (though <hi>a choſen Veſſel,</hi> and one that had as much to plead in his own behalf as any Man, Yet) <hi>counted all things but dung, that he might win Chriſt. And be found in him, not having his own Righteouſneſs, which was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107283:11"/> of the Law, but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith,</hi> Phil. 3.8,9. Miniſters muſt not be exalted in way of Derogation to the Merit and Glory of the Redeemer; for whatſoever Gifts, Graces, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Succeſs or Honour can be juſtly attributed to them, are primarily his, and their Glory is his Glory. I ſhall only add this further Remark, to clear the Wiſdom and Juſtice of God in this caſe, That and extraordinary Degree of Heavenly Glory, bears but a juſt Correſpondence to the Truſt that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Miniſters of Chriſt, and to the Honour that is put upon them in this World: They are ſtiled 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The Ambaſſadours of Chriſt, Stewards of the Myſteries of God,</hi> &amp;c. And it is but equal that thoſe ſhould be highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for diſcharging this Truſt faithfully, who muſt have ſuffered (not only the Vengeance of Eternal Fire, but) greater degrees of Shame and Torment than others, if they had perfidiouſly betray'd it.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewed what it is to turn Sinners to Rightouſneſs, and how reaſonable it is, that ſo excellent, ſo neceſſary, ſo difficult a Work, ſhould be crowned with an extraordinary Recompence; I ſhall next proceed to open the nature of that Recompence, as it is here compared to the <hi>brightneſs of the Firmament,</hi> and <hi>the ſhining of the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> But, if <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the hearts of Man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him;</hi> If the loweſt degree of Glory, do ſo far exceed the Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the moſt raiſed and refined Intellects here below, How ſhall we hope to deſcribe the heights of that excelling Glory, which ſhall be the Portion of thoſe that <hi>turn many to Righteouſneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All therefore that I ſhall attempt, is to declare ſo much of it, as is fairly deducible from this rich Similitude.</p>
            <p>Concerning which, I obſerve, firſt in the general, that there is a tow-fold Congruity in this Compariſon, between the Work of Miniſters, and their Reward.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As the Reward of Faithful Miniſters is compared to Light; and Secondly, as it is compared to the Light which is Celeſtial.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107283:12"/>
            <p>Firſt, The Compariſon of <hi>Light</hi> in general is <hi>apt,</hi> becauſe it refers clearly to their Office and Work. What more ſuitable than that thoſe who ſhined in Wiſdom and Holineſs, <hi>who bare witneſs to Jeſus Chriſt the true light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World,</hi> John 1.9. <hi>In whoſe hearts God hath ſhined, who commanded the light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, to give the light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. That theſe, I ſay, ſhould be crowned with Rays of everlaſting Light.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs obſervable, in the next place, that it is an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Shining that is made uſe of to repreſent the Rewares of Faithful Miniſters. They are the Heavenly Regions that moſt abound with Light, and in which all the great Springs and Fountains of Light are ſituate. Well then may our Minds be abſtracted from this Earthly State, and inſtantly elevated to the Superior Manſions, when we are called to contemplate the future State of thoſe that <hi>turn many to Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that were Stars both for their Light and Influence, whilſt they only aſſiſted and adorned the Church on Earth, ſhall not fail to emit more, and more glorious Beams, when fix'd in an higher Orb, when moving in a larger Sphere in the Firmament of Glory.</p>
            <p>A more particular account of what is here intended, we may gather.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> From the Oppoſition between the State here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and the Blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever, in which all the Devils and Damned Souls (and eſpecially thoſe Miniſters that wretchedly neglected the Duties of their Function) ſhall be eternally inveloped. Thoſe Priſons and Chains of Darkneſs, into which they are caſt, and in which they are faſt bound until the univerſal Appearance at the Great Judgment Day, cannot be more Black, Confounding and Diſmal, than the Robes of Light with which Faithful Miniſters muſt Shine, will be Radiant and Dazling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Difference there is between the State of Miniſters of Earth, and that which is here ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> As the latter entirely excludes the many Infelicities and Imperfection of the former.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:107283:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As it far tranſcends all the Brightneſs and Glory it can preten to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The State ſignified by <hi>the brightneſs of the Firmament,</hi> &amp;c. is a State that pefectly excludes all the Imperfections and Diſadvantages which cloud the Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt here in this World. The Heavenly Light is not only oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the thick Darkneſs of Hell, but perfectly baniſhes all the Shade and Gloomineſs of this mixed terrene State.</p>
            <p>That which is affirmed of the Righteous in general, ſhall be moſt eminently verified in <hi>thoſe that turn many to Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, they ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father,</hi> Matt. 13.43.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>They ſhall ſhine forth;</hi> Firſt, out of thoſe Clouds that their Sinful Frailties have caſt about them. Here they are Frail Sinful Men, encompaſſed with divers Infirmities, the very beſt of them not excepted; and this is more viſible in them, by reaſon of their Station, and more notably obſcures them, than any other ſort of Men. But in the Heavenly State there ſhall not be the leaſt Scar or Footſtep of any ſuch Humane Frailty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhall ſhine forth, from the Penal Conſequences of theſe Sinful Frailties, whether more immediately affecting their Perſons, or attending their Conditions and outward Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. There ſhall be <hi>no more Curſe,</hi> Rev. 22.3. no more Sickneſs and Pain upon the Body, no more Doubt nor Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure of the Spirit. Here Miniſters may be exerciſed in any kind of Affliction as well as others, and often do meet with ſharp Trials in one kind or another above others. There they ſhall be no more obſcured by the Privacy of their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, nor by the Meanneſs of their Appearance, by which many Miniſters of great Worth are either in a manner quite hidden from publick Notice, or valued at a lower Rate than otherwiſe they would or ought to be. Calumnies and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall blacken them no more; They ſhall ſhine forth of thoſe Miſts which are raiſed about them, by the Scandals com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in their Flocks, which are often conſtrued to their great Diſadvantage, though they have endeavoured never ſo much the preventing and healing of them. They ſhall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107283:13"/> ſhine forth out of thoſe Obſcurities, wherein their mutual Jealouſies, their unaccountable Diſtances and Alienations, and their interfering one with another have involved them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As this <hi>ſhining like the brightneſs of the Firmament,</hi> &amp;c. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth the Imperfections of the preſent State, ſo it eminently includes, and every way excels all the Glory wherewith they or any other Perſons do or poſſibly can ſhine in it. All the Secular Shining, the outward Grandeur that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and all other munificent Princes, have either annexed to the Miniſterial Function, or themſelves enjoyed, is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Darkneſs to that Brightneſs where with the pooreſt Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter ſhall one day ſhine and eclipſe it all for ever.</p>
            <p>And for the Spiritual Glory with which they ſhine in this Life, it ſhall be fully perfected, and as much exceed it ſelf, as the Flower and Fruit do the Seed and Root; or as the Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites of Manhood do thoſe of the Infant State; or as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Maſter-piece doth the rude Draught and firſt Lineaments of the Picture.</p>
            <p>Thus having diſcourſed concerning the Glory here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by way of Oppoſition to the Darkneſs and Horrour of the contrary State, and likewiſe in a way of Diſtinction from this preſent mortal State; I come now to treat of it as it is in it ſelf, which we ſhall find to include all that is perfect and glorious.</p>
            <p>Here we may note, firſt, What is the Subject of this Shining. Secondly, Wherein it conſiſts. Thirdly, To whom the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel ſhall ſhine. Fourthly, How long it ſhall continue.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe, 1. The entire Perſon, conſiſting of Soul and Body, ſhall <hi>ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> Both were here Sanctified, both laboured and ſuffered in the Service of our Redeemer, both were the Subjects of that Right and Claim to this Glory, which was ſpoken of before; and therefore both ſhall partake of it. The Body without the Soul is not at all capable of Glory as a moral Retribution, the Soul without the Body is not capable of compleat and conſummate Bliſs; both together therefore muſt be the adequate Subject of it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107283:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. As to the ſecond Enquiry wherein it conſiſts, it muſt be confeſſed, the formal nature of the Glory is but very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtood by us: Only this much, the Metaphor of Brightneſs and Shining doth import,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Life and Vigour: Darkneſs is as the ſhadow of Death, but Light (when applied to a rational ſubject) aſcribes an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Life to it.</item>
               <item>2. Wiſdom and Knowledge: Nothing that is Corporeal can more fully repreſent that which is Spiritual, than Light doth Knowledge: For that which the one is to Bodily Agents and Objects, that the other is to Agents and Objects Spiritual and Divine.</item>
               <item>3. It is a Symbol of Purity: Thoſe that ſhall ſhine as the Stars (according to the vulgar Acceptation) ſhall be Pure and Immaculate.</item>
               <item>4. Dignity and Honour are implied in it: Darkneſs is a Reſemblance of Debaſement and Diſhonour; but Light is an Emblem of Advancement and Glory.</item>
               <item>5. It ſignifies Beauty and Amiableneſs: <hi>Truly the Light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for the Eyes to behold the Sun,</hi> Eccl. 11.7. How pleaſant then will it be, to ſee each of theſe Stars out ſhine the Sun in its Meridian Luſtre.</item>
               <item>6. It very properly ſignifies Joy and Felicity, as Darkneſs is uſed to expreſs Sorrow and Miſery, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11. and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently accompanies them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>If we apply theſe Notions to the glorified Soul and Body, we ſhall perceive what manner of Shining is here aſcribed to them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Soul ſhall ſhine with all Intellectual Perfection: Every Faculty ſhall be exalted and refined to the higheſt pitch of which it is capable, and ſhall ſhine in the Glory and Splendour of its natural Excellency. Beſides which there is yet an higher Glory wherewith the Soul ſhall ſhine, and that is Moral Purity; or the Moral Rectitude of each Faculty in it ſelf, and of the ſeveral Faculties as they reſpect each other; whereby they are rightly diſpoſed, and regularly exert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards the Objects with which they converſe. O what a glorious Shining will there be, when all the Gifts of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107283:14"/> ſhall reſolve themſelves into one prefect Intuition, and all their Graces (ſuch as Repentance, Faith, Hope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſhall yield all their Vigour to that final Grace of Holy Love, and be wholly ſwallowed up in delightful Fruition?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Body ſhall ſhine with an admirable Corporeal Splendour: What ſhall be the Brightneſs and Beauty of the Celeſtial Body, we may partly apprehend from the ſhining of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Face when he had been with God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.33. which was ſuch, that a Vail was neceſſary to fit him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with the People, from the Glory in which our Saviour appeared upon the Mount with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> at his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration, which was too great for the choiceſt and moſt eminent of his Diſciples to bear, and could not be equalled by any Humane Skill or Artificial Glory. Somewhat we may gather from the falling of a few Rays of Heavenly Light about <hi>Saul</hi> when he was going to <hi>Damaſeus</hi> (which probably were Emanations from the Glorified Body of our Lord Jeſus.) How did this ſudden Effuſion of Heavenly Light overcome both the Light of the Sun at Noon-day, and the Sight and Spirit too of Perſecuting <hi>Saul!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſpectively each to other, the Soul and Body ſhall ſhine in a Sweet and Harmonious Accord: The Glory of the one is fitly Subſervient to the Glory of the other: The Soul is enſhrined in the Corporeal Light and Splendour of the Body, and the Body is animated all over by the Intellectual Light and Glory of the Soul: The Glory of the Soul ſhall ſhine through the Tranſparent Brightneſs of the Celeſtial Body: The Soul ſhall not abaſe the Body, nor that ſeduce the Soul any more for ever. There ſhall be an equal fitneſs in the one to command, as in the other to obey, and in both to glorifie and enjoy the God of Glory. The Spiritual Union and Agreement for the Services of that Holy State, between Soul and Body, ſhall be more exquiſite and intimate than now the Natural; and both ſhall be yet more Sacredly united to God, than they are or can be to each other. Both ſhall live, and move, and have their Beings in God, and together with Being, Life and Acting; in him they ſhall poſſeſs the Prefection of Glory. The Soul ſhines in the Celeſtial Body,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107283:14"/> the Body in the Celeſtial Society and Regions, but all in God, and God in them all, and infinitely above and beyond them: On him they all depend as the original Light; to him they are all Subordinate as the ſupream Light; to him they all conform, as to the grand exemplar of Purity. To God (and to the Lamb as immediately Subordinate) there is a conſtant Subjection and Reſignation of Perſons, Poſſeſſions and Powers, with a conſtant Reference of all Acts and Archievements to his Glory. Hence all the Beauty, Dignity and Felicity of the Heavenly State reſult eternally. This will be further explained in the next Head, in which (having conſidered the Subject of this Glory, and the formal nature of it) I come to enquire,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To whom they ſhine. Shining is a term partly relative, ſomething is ſuppoſed to be irradiated, where there is any Exhibition of Light: And ſurely that which is true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meaneſt kind and loweſt degree of Light, will not be found wanting in the higheſt Inſtances of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent kind of Light that the Univerſe affords, the Light Celeſtial. The following Particulars will ſhew what various and endleſs Reflections and Repercuſſions of Light the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Manſions are filled with.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſhine to God in his Holy Abode and Preſence. They ſhine with the Approbation and Acceptance, and to the Honour of God the Father as Creator: He will have Complacency in them, as thoſe who have Miniſtred on Earth, not to the Recovery only, but even to the Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Advancement of lapſed Creatures, above the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of that State from which they fell.</p>
            <p>God the Son our Redeemer, will be glorified in them, as thoſe who have received Authority from him, and acted under him on Earth, as he was a Prophet in revealing the Will of God; as a Prieſt in offering up Spiritual Sacrifice; of Prayer and Praiſe, and making Interceſſion for the People; and as King, in governing the ſeveral parts of the Catholick Church over which they did preſide.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt, as the Sanctifier and Comforter of Souls, will be glorified in their Glory: Becauſe they improved the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107283:15"/> Gifts and Graces received from him, in illuminating and converting the Elect of God, in Quickning, Comforting, Strengthning and Edifying them to Salvation; and in van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing and expelling all his and their Enemies. Thus does the Light of theſe Stars reflect back to the Source and Center of Light and Glory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſhall ſhine to the great Satisfaction of the Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Orders, and of the whole Heavenly Hoſt. We all know how the Angels rejoyce at the Converſion of a Sinner, and how gladly they officiate in conveying Souls to their own Calm and Bliſsful Regions, upon their Separation from the Body. With what Applauſes then will they receive the Souls of Miniſters, that were nor only Sanctified themſelves, but ſucceſsfully employed about turning others, many others, to Righteouſneſs, ſo as none of the Angels ever were. What ſpecial Interviews may be between Miniſters and the Souls they have converted, and whether any extraordinary Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe amongſt theſe Stars themſelves, I pretend not to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Only it ſeems no leſs, probable that theſe Spiritual Relations, as they ſtood on Earth; ſhould be recognized in Glory, than that thoſe ſhould which are founded in Acts purely Natural, and which were moſt immediately accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to this earthly State.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe that turn many to Righteouſneſs, ſhall ſhine to themſelves. Every one of them ſhall be a Mirrour of Divine Glory to himſelf; and ſhall find ineffable Complacency in the Views and Surveys he takes of his own perfect Rectitude and Glory.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They ſhall ſhine to the Devils and Damned Spirits. With what Regret and Anguiſh will they behold Miniſters aſcend to that Glory from which they long ſince irrecover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably fell. How will their Malignant Rage and Envy torment them, when they ſhall ſee poor deſpiſed Miniſters arrayed with everlaſting Light; and that too for the Service they have done againſt the Prince of the Kingdom of Darkneſs! Yea, and how will wicked Perſecutors gnaſh their Teeth to ſee thoſe very Men triumphing in Glory, whom they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, and baſely entreated as the Off-ſcouring of all things,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107283:15"/> and would not ſuffer to live quietly on Earth. How will all thoſe Wretches be confounded for ever, that ſhall ſee the ſelf-ſame Miniſters, as Stars ſhining with ſo tranſcendent a Luſtre, whoſe Counſels and Admonitions they rejected, and whoſe Authority, perhaps, they diſputed and diſdained to ſtoop to!</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth and laſt general Head concerns the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this Glory. Here the brighteſt Stars ſhine but for a very ſhort Seaſon, and preſently Death comes with his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Shade, which not only eclipſes but quite extinguiſhes their Light. <hi>The Prophets, do they live for ever?</hi> Zech. 1.5. but after they once come to ſhine above, as it will be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Imperfection, ſo it will be without Intermiſſion, and with out end. Sooner ſhall all the Stars in the viſible Heavens be diſrobed of their Light, than one of theſe brighter Stars ſhall ſuffer the leaſt Diminution of its Splendour. Both the Glory it ſelf, and the Eminency of it, ſhall laſt for ever: They ſhall be ever Glorious, and ever Superlatively ſo: Thoſe that are once admitted into the Preſence of God, and united to him as the Fountain of Glory can neither be ſeparated from him, nor fail of Supply, whilſt that Fountain of Light is ever overflowing. It is a Glory that not only exceeds the Merits, and is adequate to all the Capacities of its Poſſeſſors, but alſo is commenſurate to their Immortal Duration, and runs parallel with the Line of Eternity.</p>
            <p>This may ſuffice to be ſpoken concerning the Glorious Reward of Faithful Miniſters in the other World: <hi>There</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the principal Reward of all Vertue, but it is not without all Reward in this preſent State. Pleaſure and Honour the moſt Pure and Genuine, are truly inſeparable from all vertuous Actions; but they do moſt viſibly and ſenſibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend us when we are employed in doing good to others. And the greater the Good is, the more Raviſhing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that accompanies it. He that does good to the Bodies of others, finds a ſecret Exalting upon it in his own Breaſt, and is ready to confeſs that he hath more obliged himſelf by becoming a Benefactor, than thoſe to whom he was ſo, and <hi>that it is more Bleſſed to give than to receive,</hi> Acts 20.35. It is not only the more honourable Station and Office amongſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107283:16"/> Men, but hath more of a God-like Grandeur and Felicity in it. How much greater cauſe have they to rejoyce who do good to the Souls of Men, by delivering them from the moſt Savage and Mercileſs Tyranny of the Devil, and their own wicked Luſts, whoſe Vaſſals they have been, and <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into the glorious liberty of the Children of God.</hi> Thus turning Souls to Righteouſneſs is its own Reward, becauſe it includes the doing of the greateſt good to Mankind, to which all other good Works are but remotely ſubſervient.</p>
            <p>This may be lookt upon as an earneſt and fore-taſt of that ſurpaſſing Glory and Happineſs which is here promiſed. And ſo I ſhall cloſe the Doctrinal part of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>It remains that we make the beſt Practical Improvement of which the matter is capable; which ſurely is very great.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I would humbly offer to my Reverend Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Miniſtry, the clear Indications which the Text gives: 1. Of our Work: 2. Of our Reward. And thence I would infer Directions to guide us in, and Motives to quicken us to the Performance of the Duty, that we may not fall ſhort of the Reward.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſee our Work. It is not what many Miniſters aim at and buſie themſelves about, and what we are all apt enough to affect: 'Tis not, I mean, that we may gain Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe from the Populace or even from the Learned World; not to flouriſh in Riches, or in Pomp and Splendour; not to intrigue till we obtain a Dominion over our Brethren; not to Lord it over God's Heritage; not to live in eaſe and fullneſs, whatever becomes of our Work and Charge. Much leſs is it to pleaſe Men to their own unſpeakable Prejudice, by favouring them in their evil Courſes, and nouriſhing the Luſts that will prey upon them for ever. Such ends as theſe are only fit for the Miniſters of Satan, and thoſe that ſerve the God of this World, to ſeek and labour after. They are as repugnant to the Sacred Office, as they are inconſiſtent with Sincere Piety.</p>
            <p>The true and proper end of the Miniſtry, as inſtituted of God, and embraced and exerciſed by every Serious Chriſtian duly called and ſeparated to it, is <hi>to turn many to Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:107283:16"/> Other Subordinate ends we may lawfully propoſe to our ſelves, but they muſt be no further ſought, than they are truly reconcilable with the Management of our Miniſterial Work in the moſt effectual manner. So that if it ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary thereto, we ought to forego all external Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Emoluments; rather than renounce or fruſtrate it. Whatever Men account Wiſdom now, there will come a time when that Scripture ſhall take place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.30. <hi>He that winneth Souls is wiſe.</hi> He will be found to have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed his Time and Talents to the beſt Advantage for his own Comfort, the Glory of God, and the common Good of the World (which is the heighth of Wiſdom) that gaineth Souls, which otherwiſe had periſhed eternally.</p>
            <p>All Proud, Sloathful, Senſual, Worldly Miniſters, that have gained no Souls to Chriſt, but perhaps hardned them in their Impieties, ſhall one day wiſh, that they had choſen the meaneſt and baſeſt, the moſt ſervile and loborious Calling that could be found, rather than this Holy and Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable Office.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſee our Encouragement. It's an eminent Degree of eternal Glory: All our precious Light and Influence which we ſhed on others, during our momentary Labours upon Earth, will return to us again, and ennoble us for ever in Heaven. How Poor and Contemptible is all the Tinſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bravery of Popes and Cardinals, of Prelates and Princes, in compariſon of this excellent Glory? This ſhall be Verdant and Flouriſhing, when theirs is laid in the Duſt. 'Tis a hard thing to be a good Miniſter, but then it is a bleſſed thing to ſhine in Glory for ever.</p>
            <p>Let us then apply our ſelves to the Work of the Miniſtry, as thoſe that deſign, above all things, to promote the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many, by <hi>turning them to Righteouſneſs.</hi> We know, that without Holineſs none ſhall ſee the Lord; we know that Men are begotten again, to a lively hope ordinarily by the Preaching of the Goſpel; we know that if Men periſh through our Neglect, their Blood will be required of us; we know alſo that God worketh ordinarily according to the Suitableneſs of the Means, and that there is much Duty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107283:17"/> incumbent on us, to fit our Endeavours to the end we would attain by them.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Let this guide us in our Studies and Preaching. He is not the beſt Preacher that makes the loudeſt Noiſe; nor yet he that makes the fineſt Flouriſh, and garniſhes each Period with the Flowers of Rhetorick; nor he that oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly abounds with needleſs Subtilties, and ſtrives to ſhew all the Learning he has, whether the Subject require it or no. Such preach themſelves really, while they profeſs to ſet forth Jeſus Chriſt to the People: Thoſe that would <hi>turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> muſt chooſe to treat upon Subjects which their Auditors moſt needs, in a clear convincing manner, with Gravity and Seriouſneſs: They muſt feel the Power of thoſe Truths upon their own Souls, which they would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs upon others. Men of high Parts muſt deny themſelves, if need be, for the good of others, by condeſcending to the meaneſt Capacities: They muſt not think it below them to uſe familiar and plain Expreſſions, where thoſe will ſerve beſt to convey a clear Idea of the Truths of God to the Hearers. Thoſe whoſe Gifts are more ſlender muſt double their Diligence, that they may not fall too much below the Dignity of the Subjects they treat, and thereby render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Contemptible to the more Underſtanding and able ſort of Chriſtians, or to the more curious part of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſhould guide us in our Prayers for our People, and our Converſations with them. How earneſt ſhould we be with God for ſome Fruit that might <hi>abound to our account?</hi> How careful ſhould we be, not to admit any Scandalous Levity into our own carriage, nor to give countenance to it in others with whom we converſe. We are doubly ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the World, as Chriſtians, and as Miniſters; and there is a general Expectation that our Carriage be doubly ſtrict and refined, even from thoſe Freedoms which are more allowable in Perſons of a different Character. If God ſhall help us to demean our ſelves with Wiſdom, Sobriety and Godlineſs, our Converſations will doubtleſs conciliate a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for our Perſons and Labours; beſides the direct In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107283:17"/> they will have upon the Minds of thoſe that are no further acquainted with us. If the deſign of turning many to Righteouſneſs govern our Behaviour, it will make us Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient towards all, Free to converſe with the Pooreſt of the Flock, and Vigilant to lay hold on all Opportunities that may facilitate the Succeſs of our Endeavours upon them.</p>
            <p>Surely our Encouragement is every way proportionate to the Difficulties we have to encounter. We ſerve a good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, our Work is pleaſant, even when it is moſt painful to the Fleſh. We have a Promiſe of the gracious Preſence of our Lord with us, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. <hi>ult.</hi> to aſſiſt our Endeavours, to protect our Perſons, and proſper our Labours, to the end of our Lives, and to the World's end. But above all, let the Conſideration of our Reward Invigorate us, when we begin to relax our Pains, and to intermit our Labours. Let us all fire our Hearts with a noble Ambition of ſhining like the Stars for ever and ever. The more any of us are barred and excluded from Secular Honours and Preferments, let us ſo much the mote ardently aſpire after the Heavenly Glory. We have (if I miſtake not) ſome Advantage this way above others; ſince the leſs of Favour and Priviledge we enjoy in this World upon the account of our Miniſtry, others have the leſs occaſion to ſuſpect the Sincerity of our Intentions, and we may with the more Aſſurance wait for a Glorious and Unfading Crown. <hi>Wherefore, Holy Brethren, partakers of the Heavenly Calling, conſider the Apoſtle and High Prieſt of our Profeſſion Chriſt Jeſus. Who was faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in all his Houſe,</hi> Heb.3.1,2.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Redeemer was not only a Pattern of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Virtues, as they are common to every Station, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of Miniſterial Prudence, Zeal, Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Fidelity; Diligence, and all under the greateſt Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements from that Polity under which he lived, and from the Grandees of that People with whom and for whole Benefit he ſpent his Labours and ſhed his Blood. His gentle treating of thoſe that were weak, but willing to learn their Duty; his gradual diſcovery of Chriſtian Verities as they could be born; his ſharp and plain rebuking of thoſe that ſtrutted in a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107283:18"/> Garb of Phariſaical Sanctity, but malign'd his Perſon and Deſign, and made it their buſineſs to ſeduce others; his Compaſſion to Souls, and eaſineſs of Acceſs to the poorer ſort, were all intended and are all recorded for our Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>Let us alſo confider <hi>Daniel</hi> and all the Holy Prophets, with the Apoſtles and Primitive Biſhops; Let us conſider the many Holy Lights that adorned the Church ſince the Reformation, and particularly the Brittiſh Churches. Let their Zeal and Conſtancy live in us, and be tranſmitted by us with all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to thoſe that ſhall ſucceed us. Let us conſider the Example of our Reverend deceaſed Brother, whom if I reckon amongſt the chiefeſt of thoſe Modern Worthies that have turned many to Righteouſneſs, and do now <hi>ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> I doubt not to have the Suffrages of all that hear me, and of all that knew him.</p>
            <p>He was a Perſon of good natural Parts, one that had enough of a Genius to maſter what he applied himſelf to, and to make up the Figure of a great Man: Theſe natural Abilities were cultivated by extraordinary Induſtry, which begun very early, and continued all his Life; witneſs the many Volumes which he has left behind him written with his own hand. He was moſt converſant in thoſe parts of Learning which are directly Subſervient to Divinity, and made great uſe thereof in all his Compoſures; but with ſo little Affectation, that the Unlearned were never amuſed with it, and yet the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious part of his Auditory had no lack of it. His Parts and Learning were both admirably ſet off by a ſingular Fitneſs for Friendſhip and Converſation, in which he was amiable above many. His Temper was Sincere, Candid, and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous to and beyond his Power: His Diſcourſe was Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, Innocent, Pleaſant, and Profitable to a high degree. His Deportment was Grave, yet Sweet and Obliging. Theſe Vertues were lodged in a Soul truly Chriſtian. I know we muſt make ſome Allowance for Humane Infirmities, from which none are exempt whilſt they are in the Body. He was but a Candidate for the State of Perfection, and <hi>was a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107283:18"/> Man ſubject to like Paſſions as we are,</hi> which he hath now put off, together with Mortality.</p>
            <p>But certainly this notwithſtanding, He had a truly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Spirit, and did abound in choice Experiences of God's Dealings with himſelf and others. His Life was filled up with a Uniform Series of Faithful Services to God and to his Generation. He did not <hi>load Men with heavy Burdens, which he would not touch with one of his Fingers;</hi> but put his own Neck into the ſame Chriſtian Yoke, which he exhorted others to take upon them.</p>
            <p>Beſides his Exemplary Behaviour as a Chriſtian in general, deſigning and doing all the Good he was capable of to the Souls and Bodies of Men, he was highly imitable in his Domeſtick Relations. He was (and will ever be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to have been) a moſt kind and tender Husband to his Yoke-fellow, a loving and faithful Father to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, a gentle and juſt Maſter to his Servants, and moſt preciſely Regular in the Religious Conduct of his Family.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt and beſt part of his Character (his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſuppoſed) is this, That he was <hi>an Able and Faithful Miniſter of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter but of the Spirit.</hi> He reflected Honour to the Sacred Function, as well as received Honour from it. He was Faithful to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Vow, and did not Sacrilegiouſly alienate himſelf from the Work to which he was ſolemnly devoted. When the Law deprived him of the Temple, and publick Maintenance to which he ſtood related, he quietly gave place. But he judged not that this did or could either diſcharge him from his Miniſterial Vow, or diſſolve the Relation betwixt him and his People.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, with all Meekneſs and Simplicity, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Spirit of Oppoſition, he proceeded in his Work amongſt that People to which he had ſo clear and univerſal a Call; paying all Deference to the Civil Magiſtrate, ſo far as he could, without violating his Conſcience. In this way of Sober Conſcientious Non conformity to the Engliſh Dioceſan Prelacy, Subſcriptions and Ceremonies, he caſt himſelf and his Family purely upon Providence, and lived
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107283:19"/> upon it all his days. Nor was the Divine Providence want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to raiſe him up many kind Benefactors, whoſe Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality ſupplied the Want of a Legal Maintenance. Theſe were his Sentiments, and this his Practiſe. But he was, nevertheleſs, a Perſon of ſingular Moderation: He had both a large Charity and great Veneration for thoſe that differed from him, if they were Men of Worth, and Unblameable in their Lives. They can teſtifie this, that know what a fair and amicable Correſpondence he maintained with many of his Reverend Conforming Brethren, to ſeveral of whom this Good Man's Name was perhaps as Precious, and his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety as grateful, as if he had been one of their own Stamp. But his Moderation towards thoſe that diſſented from him, was not more Eminent, than his Condeſcention to the Juniors in the Miniſtry, and to thoſe that were, upon many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, much Inferior to him. He took great Pleaſure in Converſing with Hopeful Young Miniſters, and never failed to give them all the Reſpect and Encouragement that was either due to them, or convenient for them. He was very Free and Familiar with thoſe of his more intimate Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and upon all Occaſions would expreſs both a Paternal Care of them, and Affection to them. How may I and ſome others cry out upon this occaſion, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did when he ſaw the Tranſlation of <hi>Elijah, My Father, my Father, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Horſe-men thereof,</hi> 2 Kings 2.12.</p>
            <p>Our Reverend and Dear Father is taken from us, whoſe Authority we revered, and whoſe Indulgent Care over us was one of our greateſt Supports. Nor was he only an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Miniſter at large, but a Prudent Vigilant Paſtor to a numerous Flock that dearly loved him, and was no leſs dearly beloved of him. How Solicitous was he for the Peace and Holineſs of his People? How was his Soul grieved, and what an Holy Solicitude ſeized him, when any Scandalous Sin was committed amongſt them; and how Tenderly and Faithfully, and (through the Divine Goodneſs) how ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully did he treat with Offenders, <hi>to recover them,</hi> by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>out of the Snare of the Devil?</hi> Yet though he was a Perſon of ſuch Wiſdom and Sufficiency, as we all knew him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107283:19"/> to be, yet none could be more Diffident of himſelf, or more diſpoſed to ask the Advice of others. He rarely came to a Reſolution about any momentous Affair, till he had firſt conſulted with his Brethren in the Miniſtry, or the more Intelligent part of his own Congregation. By this means, and the good Service he did amongſt them, he had ſo great an Intereſt in his Peoples Affections, that they ſcarce knew how to refuſe any thing that he thought fit to urge them to. The ample Contributions of his Hearers, at his Motion, to all the great occaſions of Charity that have been of late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, are publick and undeniable Evidences of this Truth.</p>
            <p>But his particular Excellency is yet behind. He was one of the moſt Powerful Profitable Preachers that ever theſe Parts were acquainted with: In other things he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded moſt others, but in this he exceeded himſelf. There be many Excellencies belonging to a Preacher, each of which ſingly might be ſufficient to render a Perſon Uſeful and Eminent, that were all combined in him. His Matter was ſolid and weighty, and of a Practical Tendency to change Mens Natures and Reform their Lives. He was not for novel undigeſted Speculations. He ſtudiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined Controverſie at all times, but eſpecially in the Pulpit. Nor did he make it his buſineſs to reflect upon the different Parties amongſt Proteſtants: Inſtead of that, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, with all his Strength, to declare Divine Truths with ſo convincing an Evidence, and to enforce his Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations with ſuch irreſiſtible Arguments, and with ſuch poinant Expreſſions, as might leave the Hearers under ſtrong Convictions concerning the Neceſſity of Holineſs. And O how had God fitted him for this great Work, and how did the Lord own him in the Proſecution of it? How would he lay open the Deceits of Mens Hearts? How would he expoſe the Devices whereby Satan commonly deludes and deſtroys Sinners? He often penetrated ſo far into the ſecret Receſſes of the Soul, and deſcribed the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, Birth and Progreſs of Sin in ſuch lively Colours,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107283:20"/> that one would have thought he had not only been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the outward Commiſſion of it, but that he had lain in Mens Boſoms, and inſpected all the moſt ſecret Tranſactions there. And yet I know not whether he was more Happy in this, or in opening to Penitents a Door of Hope, when they were once thoroughly awakened, and pouring the Oyl of Conſolation into their Bleeding Wounds. <hi>He was a Meſſenger, an Interpreter, one among a thouſand, to ſhew unto Man his Uprightneſs,</hi> Job 33.23. His Sermons were plain and diſcourſive, and full of Holy Zeal and Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; but withal ſo embelliſhed with notable Maxims and curious Obſervations, ſo illuſtrated with pat Similitudes and Examples, and delivered with ſuch a Propriety, Facility, and Fluency of Expreſſion, and with ſo graceful a Mean and Geſture, as rendered the plaineſt Matter no leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable than it was neceſſary. Nor did he only entertain his Hearers with that which was good in it ſelf, but with what was ſeaſonable and proper. He was very Inquiſitive and Obſervant about the State of his Country, and the Providences of God towards it, and about the Condition and Carriage of his Flock; to both which he did accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate his Diſcourſes with ſingular Judgment and Dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. In this he was moſt Impartial, and would inveigh with equal Freedom againſt the Faults of the Rich as of the Poor. Nor was he only an excellent popular Preacher; he was alſo an able Expoſitor of Holy Scripture. The Solutions he produceth to the Difficulties of the Text, were clear and Satisfactory; the Expoſitions ſound and weighty; the Obſervations fine, and, many times, ſuch as do not ordinarily occur; and the whole performed with an Eaſe and Elegancy peculiar to himſelf. What Method ſoever he followed, he ſpake with Authority and Majeſty; <hi>His words were as goads and as nails faſtned by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Aſſemblies, which are given from one Shepherd,</hi> Eccl. 12.11.</p>
            <p>I am well aſſured under his Miniſtry, if ever in theſe latter days, that ſaying of the Apoſtle received a bleſſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107283:20"/> Accompliſhment in many Inſtances (allowing for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparity between the Gifts beſtowed in ſuch diſtant Ages of the Church) <hi>But if all Propheſie, and there come in one that believeth not, or one unlearned, he is convinced of all, he is judged of all. And thus are the Secrets of his Heart made manifeſt; and ſo falling down on his face, he will worſhip God, and report that God is in you of a truth,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.24. Many that have come to hear him accidentally, or out of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, have both experienced and declared much of this nature.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God to honour his Miniſtry with ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Succeſs, that great numbers, where-ever he reſided, were at leaſt viſibly reclaimed by it; and many of thoſe (we have great reaſon to judge) really changed into the Divine Image; concerning whom he might ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Though ye have ten thouſand Inſtructors in Christ, yet have ye not many Fathers; for in Christ Jeſus I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten you though the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.15. For the Truth of all this I appeal to you all, and to all that knew him, or almoſt ever heard of him. I appeal to that univerſal Eſteem and Reverence that was paid him by Perſons of all Ranks high and low; of all ſorts, good and bad; of all Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>I do not preſent you with this account of this Eminent and Faithful Servant of Chriſt, as if it were a full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Character of him, No, that would require a larger compaſs, and an abler manage than I can give it. This may ſuffice to be ſpoken at the preſent, to the honour of Divine Grace, manifeſting it ſelf in ſo uſeful an Inſtrument. May it alſo provoke us to bleſs God for him, and kindle in us an Emulation of his Attainments, and of the Succeſs that attended his Labours.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Inference concerns the ſurviving Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. A juſt Senſe all ought to have of this great Loſs, and therefore it may well be indulged to you that are the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107283:21"/> greateſt Sufferers by it. But let us not mourn as thoſe that have no Hope, but rather as Perſons aſſured, that his Soul, whoſe removal we lament, does already ſhine as a Star of the firſt Magnitude, and enjoys the Bleſſed Reward of all his Labours.</p>
            <p>The Stroke indeed is heavy, the Breach is wide, and never to be forgotten, never (I fear) to be repaired upon every account. But ſeeing our Loſs is his Gain, why ſhould not his Gain be our Comfort? He is exalted to an higher Orb, and moves in a more glorious Sphere than ever. And if God receive Glory from him in a more excellent way, and he alſo be dignified and made Happy after a more excellent manner than was poſſible on Earth, Why ſhould you or any of us Repine? It was a removal that muſt be at one time or another, and God hath determined this to be the fitteſt Seaſon; Do you therefore acquieſce in what he hath done, and ſtudy to improve this Providence to a greater Fitneſs for your own Change. Though his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence be withdrawn, his Example, his Inſtructions, and his Prayers, I hope, will be always beneficial to you, and in ſome meaſure ſupply the want of it. The ſame God that made his preſence uſeful, can make his abſence ſo, and he it is that muſt do all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third Inference reſpects the People from whom he was taken: And they are of two ſorts; Firſt, Such as have not turned to Righteouſneſs, notwithſtanding all the earneſt Calls and Invitations which this Ambaſſador of Chriſt hath given them. They have been <hi>like the deaf Adder that ſtoppeth her ear; which will not hearken to the Voice of the Charmer, charm he never ſo wiſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay, you have loſt one of the moſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Seaſons that ever any enjoyed, for the Converſion of your Souls. You ſhall hear the Voice of this powerful Orator no more for ever: He muſt ſollicit, warn, exhort you no more. O recollect the moving Language, the Holy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107283:21"/> mellifluous Oratory wherewith he would have conquered your obſtinate Hearts, that he might eſpouſe you to one Husband, Jeſus Chriſt. How did he purſue you from time to time, longing to ſee Jeſus Chriſt formed in you. Are you not aſhamed and terribly afraid what will become of you, when you conſider how many he prevailed upon, and yet you remain in your Sins? O that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe things might ſo revive upon you, that being dead, he may yet ſpeak to the awakening and ſaving of your Souls? Nay, How Happy would it be yet for you, and what an Alleviation to your preſent Grief, if the Senſe of God's Diſpleaſure, in taking away this great Light from us, might cloath his Funerals with the Virtue of an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſo as to effect that Bleſſed Change upon you, which was in vain attempted by all other means? Know you not that you muſt give a ſtrict account of all the Sermons you have heard, and of all the Convictions you have had under his Miniſtry?</p>
            <p>Hear, all you that are Drunkards, Fornicators, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, Sabbath-breakers; all that are Covetous, all that indulge their Furious Paſſions, or that live in any other Notorious Sin; and know, that you, <hi>even you,</hi> muſt turn unto Righteouſneſs, or periſh everlaſtingly. O dare not, then, to meet this Servant of Chriſt at the great Judgment-day, in an unconverted State; for, if you do, he will be a ſwift and terrible Witneſs againſt you. How will he be ready to ſay, Lord, theſe are the Wretches, that I ſo often, ſo long, and ſo earneſtly treated with, about the Salvation of their precious Souls, and all in vain. I required them in thy Name, and in obedience to thy Authority, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and turn; I beſought them; I conjured them by the Mercies of God, by the Meritorious Bloodſhed of Jeſus Chriſt, by the invaluable Worth of their own Immortal Souls; I opened the Goſpel-Covenant to them; I ſhewed them the terms of Life; I ſet the Promiſes and Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Life and Death, Heaven and Hell before them; I directed them to ſeek the Aids of thy Holy Spirit; I told
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107283:22"/> them of this very day, when they and I ſhould meet at this thy Tribunal, to receive an irreverſible Sentence, but they believed not my Report. I travelled over them, I ſpent my Labours and Life upon them, to have broken their Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine Hearts; <hi>I ſought to find out acceptable words, even words of Truth;</hi> I endeavoured to ſhew them their Miſery, and to diſcover the Remedy provided in the Goſpel. But all that I could obtain was a verbal Commendation. <hi>Lo I was unto them as a very lovely Song, of one that hath a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Voice, and can play well on an Inſtrument, for they heard my words, but they did them not.</hi> Sinners, <hi>when this cometh to paſs, (lo, it will come) ſhall you not then know,</hi> to your Coſt, <hi>that a Prophet hath been amongst you?</hi> Ezek. 33.32,33. <hi>What will ye do in the day of Viſitation, and in the Deſolation which ſhall come from far, to whom will ye flee for help? and where will you leave your Glory?</hi> Iſa. 10.3.</p>
            <p>The other part of the People from which he is taken, conſiſts of thoſe that have <hi>turned to Righteouſneſs.</hi> Many ſuch went before him to poſſeſs that Glory which was revealed to them, and for which they were prepared by this Bleſſed Inſtrument. Theſe have already experienced the Truth of what he told them, and are Partners with him in the Sacred Pleaſures of Paradiſe. My buſineſs, therefore, is with thoſe that are left behind in this Vale of Tears: And of ſuch I ſay, Bleſſed are ye of the Lord. You have cauſe to praiſe God, that ever you ſaw his Face, or heard his Voice, and ſhall praiſe the Free and Rich Grace of God to all Eternity. You ſuſtain a mighty Loſs, in that you muſt not be brought up under his Wing, whoſe Labours firſt begat in you the Seed and Principle of the Divine Life. I know you will be more ſenſibly affected with this Loſs than others, becauſe of the Love you bare to him as to a Spiritual Father, and that you will (as you have juſt cauſe) honour his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory whilſt you have a day to live.</p>
            <p>But this is not enough for Perſons in your Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: Your Dear Paſtor is raviſhed from you, Death
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107283:22"/> hath ſilenced him, and bereaved you. But ſhould not you and I then ſearch our Hearts, and be humbled for thoſe Sins which have provoked God to make this ſore breach upon us and the whole Church, after ſeveral others, each of which was very deplorable; but all together much more are and ought to be for a Lamentation.</p>
            <p>Have we not cauſe to apprehend ſome Judgment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, and that theſe Dear Servants of God are <hi>taken away from the evil to come?</hi> O labour after Perſeverance in the Profeſſion of the Truth, and to make good Proficiency in the ways of Godlineſs. So ſhall you ſee the Face of your Paſtor again to your mutual Joy, and ſhall be a Crown to him in the day of Chriſt, when he ſhall ſtand forth and ſay, <hi>Behold I, and the Children which the Lord hath given me.</hi> Encourage and ſtrengthen each other; your being deprived of ſo conſiderable an Help, ſhould put you upon the more diligent Improvement of thoſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which remain: Your Concord and Harmony, your Holy and Unblamable Deportment, your humble Supplications to Almighty God for the Aids of his Holy Spirit to your ſelves, and for a double Portion thereof upon thoſe that ſucceed in the room of this once gracious and now glorified Saint and Miniſter, may be a propitious Token to us, that our God will not utterly forſake us; that he hath Mercy in ſtore for us, and will <hi>give us a Nail in his Holy Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall remit you for a concluding Paſſage to <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7,8,9. <hi>Remember them which have the Rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the Word of God, whoſe Faith follow conſidering the end of their Converſation. Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever. Be not carried about with divers and ſtrange Doctrines, for it is a good thing that the Heart be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed with Grace, not with Meats, which have not profited them which have been occupied therein.</hi> Verſe 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule ever you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account, that they
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107283:23"/> may do it with Joy, and not with Grief; for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> Verſe 20, 21. <hi>Now the God of Peace, which brought again from the Dead, our Lord Jeſus, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work, to do his Will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Christ, to whom be Glory for ever and ever. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>Baxter</hi> on the New Teſtament.</item>
               <item>1. The New Creature: Opening the Nature, Properties and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, of that great Work of the New Creation upon the Souls of Men.</item>
               <item>2. Family Altar: A Treatiſe to promote the Worſhip of God in Private Houſes.</item>
               <item>3. The Beſt Intall: Or Dying Parents Living Hopes for their Surviving Children.</item>
               <item>4. Meetneſs for Heaven: Diſcovering the Nature and Neceſſity of Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Actual Meetneſs for Heaven here. By Mr. <hi>Oliver Heywood</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</item>
               <item>Above Thirty Diſcourſes on ſeveral Doctrinal and Practical Subjects, juſt finiſhing from the Preſs, in large Follo, of the late Reverend and Learned Divine <hi>David Clerkſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Annotations on the whole Bible, by Mr. <hi>Matt. Pool,</hi> and ſeveral other Learned Divines, the third Edition, with large Contents to the Chapters, and a Concordance</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Baxter':</hi> Life, written by his own Hand, publiſh'd by Mr. <hi>Silveſter,</hi> is at the Preſs.</item>
               <item>A Body of Practical Divinity, in about 176 Sermons on the Aſſemblies Catechiſm, by <hi>Tho. Watſon</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Earneſt Call to Family Religion: Being the Subſtance of eighteen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. By <hi>Samuel Slater</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
